Levi P. Morton Correspondence
Levi P. Morton Correspondence
1860-1912
Morton, Levi P. (Levi Parsons), 1824-1920.
0.5 linear ft.
Papers of the Congressman from New York, United States minister to France, Vice-President of the United States, and Republican governor of New York State. Collection contains mostly incoming correspondence from clergymen, educators, financiers, journalists, and politicians. Some letters are addressed to Morton's executive secretary, Ashley W. Cole.
149382
Biographical History
Levi P. Morton (1824-1920) was a Congressman from New York (1879-1881), United States minister to France (1881-1885), Republican governor of New York State (1895-1896), and Vice President of the United States (1889-1893) under President Benjamin Harrison.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Levi P. Morton Correspondence is a collection of mostly incoming letters dated between 1860 and 1912, the bulk of which were written during Morton's tenure as Governor of New York (1895-1896). Morton's correspondents include authors and journalists (Henry Abbey, Lyman Abbott, W.J. Arkell, George W. Childs, Edwin L. Godkin, Frances M. Harris (pseud. Hope Ledyard), St. Clair McKelway, Oswald Ottendorfer, Franz Sigel, William Allen White); as well as clergymen (Thomas K. Beecher, Arthur C. Coxe, Theodore L. Cuyler, William C. Doane, John Hall, F.D. Huntington, John Ireland, Abram N. Littlejohn, Charles H. Parkhurst, H.C. Potter); educators (Nicholas M. Butler, Henry M. MacCracken, Jacob Schurman, Booker T. Washington, Alexander S. Webb); and financiers (Collis P. Huntington, Russell Sage, William C. Whitney). The bulk of the correspondence is from fellow politicians (William B. Allison, Cornelius N. Bliss, George S. Boutwell, Simon Cameron, Chauncey M. Depew, Roswell P. Flower, Frank W. Higgins, Elihu Root), including a number of state governors: R.A. Alger (Michigan), James A. Beaver (Pennsylvania), Charles A. Culberson (Texas), Charles W. Lippitt (Rhode Island), W.J. Stone (Missouri), and H.M. Wells (Utah).
Many of the letters (W.S. Bissell, William A. Butler, Joseph Choate, John Hall, MacCracken, Sage, Sigel, Benjamin F. Tracy) relate to particular pieces of legislation before the then-Governor, the largest number in reference to the Greater New York bill, an effort to consolidate Brooklyn and New York into one large metropolitan area (Abbott, Cuyler, C.P. Huntington, Littlejohn, Parkhurst, Potter, William C. Redfield). Also among the letters are several lengthy opinions (James C. Carter, Choate, Joseph Larocque, Root) which Morton solicited regarding the selection of appellate judges for the State Supreme Court. Among other issues discussed in the correspondence are public school reform (N.M. Butler, Doane, Root); separation of church and state (John Ireland); protection of the State forests (Gifford Pinchot, Nathan Straus); establishment of the State Veterinary College at Cornell University (Schurman); and prison reform (Beecher, F.D. Huntington). One of the most interesting of the incoming letters is an item from the Navy Department secretary M.A. Herbert, who upon learning of the State's plans to widen the Erie Canal, Suggests (3 Jan. 1896):
The moderate depth of water in the Erie Canal would prevent the passage of most naval vessels now in service, but with the width of locks increased to 23 feet it would be possible that a class of ships built especially for the defense of the lakes could be kept in New York, ready for service on the lakes in case of hostilities with Great Britain. Our treaty with that country limits its naval force on the lakes to one gunboat, but should the Erie Canal be available, the present advantage of Great Britain, the possession of a waterway through its own territory, would be counterbalanced and the defense of our Northern frontier simplified.
In addition there are a few letters of introduction (0.E. Babcock, Lucius Fairchild, Ottendorfer, Edward Thornton, M.R. Waite) and numerous recommendations for various appointments (J.W. De Peyster, S.B. Elkins, John G. Evans, F.M. Finch, Hamilton Fish, Flower, William P. Frye, Higgins, Frank Hiscock, Horatio C. King, Warner Miller, Sage, James W. Wadsworth, George L. Wellington, Stewart L. Woodford).
Arrangement of the Collection
Letters are arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
Related Material
has many manuscript collections relating to New York State politics and history. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Politics, government and public administration; Abbey, Henry, 1842-1911.; Abbott, Lyman, 1835-1922.; Alger, R. A. (Russell Alexander), 1836-1907.; Allison, William B. (William Boyd), 1829-1908.; Arkell, W. J. (William J.), 1856-1930.; Babcock, Orville Elias, 1835-1884.; Baird, Absalom, 1824-1905.; Beaver, James A. (James Addams), 1837-1914.; Beecher, Thomas Kinnicut, 1824-1900.; Bissell, Wilson Shannon, 1847-1903.; Bliss, Cornelius Newton, 1833-1911.; Boutwell, George S. (George Sewall), 1818-1905.; Butler, Matthew Calbraith, 1836-1909.; Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947.; Butler, William Allen, 1825-1902.; Cameron, Simon, 1799-1889.; Carter, James C. (James Coolidge), 1827-1905.; Carter, Thomas Henry, 1854-1911.; Chandler, William E. (William Eaton), 1835-1917.; Childs, George William, 1829-1894.; Choate, Joseph Hodges, 1832-1917.; Clay, Cassius Marcellus, 1810-1903.; Cole, Ashley W., 1841-1920.; Coxe, A. Cleveland (Arthur Cleveland), 1818-1896.; Croes, J. J. R. (John James Robertson), 1834-1906.; Culberson, Charles A. (Charles Allen), 1855-1925.; Cuyler, Theodore L. (Theodore Ledyard), 1822-1909.; Davis, Cushman Kellogg, 1838-1900.; Depew, Chauncey M. (Chauncey Mitchell), 1834-1928.; De Peyster, J. Watts (John Watts), 1821-1907.; Doane, William Croswell, 1832-1913.; Doremus, Robert Ogden, 1824-1906.; Egan, Patrick, 1841-; Elkins, Stephen B. (Stephen Benton), 1841-1911.; Evans, John Gary, 1863-1942.; Fairchild, Lucius, 1831-1896.; Finch, Francis M. (Francis Miles), 1827-1907.; Flint, Austin, 1836-1915.; Flower, Roswell Pettibone, 1835-1899.; Frye, William P. (William Pierce), 1831-1911.; Godkin, Edwin Lawrence, 1831-1902.; Hale, Eugene, 1836-1918.; Hall, John, 1829-1898.; Harris, F. McCready (Frances McCready); Herbert, Hilary A. (Hilary Abner), 1834-1919.; Higgins, Frank Wayland, 1856-1907.; Hunt, Richard Morris, 1828-1895.; Huntington, Collis P. (Collis Potter), 1821-1900.; Huntington, F. D. (Frederic Dan), 1819-1904.; Ireland, John, 1838-1918.; King, Horatio C. (Horatio Collins), 1837-1918.; Lamont, Daniel Scott, 1851-1905.; Lippitt, Charles Warren, 1846-1924.; Littlejohn, Abram Newkirk, 1824-1901.; MacCracken, Henry Mitchell, 1840-1918.; McKelway, St. Clair, 1905-1980.; Metcalf, Lorettus Sutton, 1837-1920.; Miller, Warner, 1838-1918.; Olney, Richard, 1835-1917.; Ottendorfer, Oswald, 1826-1900.; Parkhurst, Charles H. (Charles Henry), 1831-1889.; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946.; Porter, Horace, 1837-1921.; Potter, Henry Codman, 1835-1908.; Redfield, William Cox, 1858-1932.; Reed, Thomas B. (Thomas Brackett), 1839-1902.; Rhodes, James Ford, 1848-1927.; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937.; Ruger, Thomas Howard, 1833-1907.; Sage, Russell, 1816-1906.; Schurman, Jacob Gould, 1854-1942.; Scribner, G. Hilton (Gilbert Hilton), 1831-1910.; Seward, Clarence A. (Clarence Armstrong), 1828-1897.; Seward, Frederick William, 1830-1915.; Sigel, Franz, 1824-1902.; Stone, William Joel, 1848-1918.; Straus, Nathan, 1848-1931.; Tracy, Benjamin F. (Benjamin Franklin), 1830-1915.; Waite, Morrison R. (Morrison Remick), 1816-1888.; Walcott, Charles D. (Charles Doolittle), 1850-1927.; Wanamaker, John, 1838-1922.; Waring, George E. (George Edwin), 1833-1898.; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915.; Webb, Alexander S. (Alexander Stewart), 1835-1911.; Wellman, Francis L. (Francis Lewis), 1854-1942.; Weston, Edward Payson, 1839-1929.; Whitney, William C. (William Collins), 1841-1904.; Williams, Henry Shaler, 1847-1918.; Woodford, Stewart L. (Stewart Lyndon), 1835-1913.; Republican Party (N.Y.); Governors -- New York (State); Patronage, Political -- New York (State); New York (State) -- History -- 1865-; New York (State) -- Officials and employees -- Selection and appointment.; New York (State) -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950.; New York (N.Y.) -- Politics and government -- To 1898.; Correspondence.; Governors.; Politicians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Abbey, Henry, 1895; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Abbott, Lyman, 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Alger, Russell Alexander, 1895; 1896; 2 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Allison, William Boyd, 1895; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Arkell, William J., undated; 1 outgoing letter (Box 1)
  - Babcock, Orville Elias, 1873; 1 outgoing letter (Box 1)
  - Baird, Absalom, 1894; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Beach, L. H., 1886?; 1 outgoing letter (Box 1)
  - Beaver, James A., 1894; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Beecher, Thomas Kinnicut, 1895; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Bissell, Wilson Shannon, 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Bliss, Cornelius Newton, 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Boutwell, George Sewall, 1894; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Burney, Hiram, 1860; 1 outgoing letter (Box 1)
  - Butler, Matthew Galbraith, 1894; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1894; 1896; 2 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Butler, William Allen, 1895; 1896; 2 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Cameron, Simon, 1883; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Carter, James Coolidge, 1895; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Carter, Thomas Henry, 1894; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Chandler, William Eaton, 1895; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Childs, George William, 1892; 1 outgoing letter (Box 1)
  - Choate, Joseph Hodges, 1895; 1896; 3 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Clay, Cassius Marcellus, 1862; 1 outgoing letter (Box 1)
  - Cornwell, George, 1887; 1896; 2 outgoing letters (Box 1)
  - Coxe, Arthur Cleveland, undated; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Croes, John James Robertson, 1895; 1 outgoing letter (Box 1)
  - Culberson, Charles Allen, 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Cuyler, Theodore Ledyard, 1895; 1896; 2 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Davis, Cushman Kellogg, 1895; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Depew, Chauncey Mitchell, 1894; 1895; 2 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - De Peyster, John Watts, 1895; 2 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Doane, William Croswell, 1894; 1896,; 1898,; undated; 5 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Doremus, Robert Ogden, 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Egan, Patrick, 1894; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Elkins, Stephen Benton, 1895; 1896; 2 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Evans, John Gary, 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Fairchild, Lucius, 1881; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Finch, Francis Miles, 1895; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Fish, Hamilton, 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Flint, Austin, 1894; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Flower, Roswell Pettibone, 1894; 1896; 2 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Frye, William Pierce, undated; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Godkin, Edwin Lawrence, 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Hale, Eugene, undated; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Hall, John, 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Harris, Frances McCready, 1895; 3 incoming letters, 4 related letters and a clipping (Box 1)
  - Herbert, Hilary Abner, 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Higgins, Frank Wayland, 1896; 2 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Hiscock, Frank, 1895; 2 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Hunt, Richard Morris, 1895; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Huntington, Collis Potter, 1895; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Huntington, Frederic Dan, 1895; 1896; 2 incoming letters and 1 enclosure (Box 1)
  - Ireland, John, 1895; 1896; 2 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Jackson, W. E., 1888; 1 outgoing letter (Box 1)
  - King, E. S., 1890; 1 outgoing letter (Box 1)
  - King, Horatio Collins, 1896; 2 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Knapp, J. N., 1888; 2 outgoing letters (Box 1)
  - Lamont, Daniel Scott, 1896; 2 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Larocque, Joseph, 1895; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Ledyard, Hope, See Harris, Frances McCready.
  - Lippitt, Charles Warren, 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Littlejohn, Abram Newkirk, 1895; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - MacCracken, Henry Mitchell, 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - McKelway, St. Clair, 1895; 1896; 2 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Metcalf, Lorettus Sutton, 1887; 1 outgoing letter (Box 1)
  - Miller, Warner, 1895; 1896; 3 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Nordhoff, Mr., 1873?; 1 outgoing letter (Box 1)
  - Olney, Richard, 1895; 1896; 8 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Ottendorfer, Oswald, 1895; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Parkhurst, Charles Henry, 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Patten, Mary, undated; 1 outgoing letter (Box 1)
  - Pinchot, Gifford, 1894; 2 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Ponsonby, Arthur C., 1894; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Porter, Horace, 1895; 2 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Potter, Henry Codman, 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Redfield, William C., 1896; 1 incoming letter and 2 related documents (Box 1)
  - Reed, Thomas Brackett, 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Rhodes, James Ford, undated; 1 outgoing letter (Box 1)
  - Root, Elihu, 1895; 1896; 3 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Ruger, Thomas Howard, 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Sage, Russell, 1894; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Sargent, Mr., undated; 1 outgoing letter (Box 1)
  - Schurman, Jacob Gould, 1894; 1895,; 1896; 4 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Scribner, Gilbert Hilton, undated; 1 outgoing letter (Box 1)
  - Seward, Clarence Armstrong, 1887; 1 outgoing letter (Box 1)
  - Seward, Frederick William, 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Sigel, Franz, 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Stewart, John R., 1911; 1912; 2 outgoing letters (Box 1)
  - Stone, William Joel, 1895; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Straus, Nathan, 1895; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Thornton, Edward, 1894; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Townsend, [ ], 1895; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Tracy, Benjamin Franklin, 1894; 1896; 2 incoming letters (Box 1)
  - Wadsworth, James W., 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Waite, Morrison Remick, 1882; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Walcott, Charles Doolittle, 1895; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Wanamaker, John, 1892; 1 outgoing letter (Box 1)
  - Waring, George Edwin, 1895; 1 incoming letter and 1 related document (Box 1)
  - Washington, Booker T., 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Webb, Alexander Stewart, 1895; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Wellington, George L., 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Wells, Heber Manning, 1896; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Weston, Edward Payson, 1894; 1896; 2 incoming letters and 1 clipping (Box 1)
  - Whitney, William Collins, 1894; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Williams, Henry Shaler, 1895; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Woodford, Stewart Lyndon, 1895; 1 incoming letter (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, 1901; 1896,; undated; 2 outgoing letters and 1 fragment addressed to Griswold (Box 1)